foreign
[Music]
hello from Jonathan how do you recommend
navigating supplements multivitamins
protein barriers I'm not sure what to
trust give me the lacks regulation
absolutely well certainly there's this
regulation is indeed lacks I have a
bunch of videos about that
um so what protein powder to get no
protein powder why would anyone need
protein powder to get protein same way
you get carb same way you get fat from a
Whole Foods ideally hold plant Foods
um and no reason to take a multivitamin
um there are some things that people may
need in supplement form
um so for example vitamin D for getting
interact with sunshine vitamin B12
you're not eating vitamin B12 45 Foods
um so how do you get supplements that
aren't like contaminated with something
or actually have what they say they have
um probably the best one best way to do
it is to get one that is USP certified
so it's a third-party certification
entity that makes sure that whatever
says on the label is what is actually in
the bottle doesn't mean it's good for
you or anything I mean they you kind of
USB certification of snake oil but at
least it would be actual snake oil at
the dose that they say on the package so
it's kind of truth in advertising
okay this is from Heidi new the
plant-based mostly fruit diet okay
I need to take vitamin B12 supplement
absolutely or evine B12 fortified Foods
one of those two
um critically important for anyone
eating a plant-centered diet even if
you're not
um even if it's not strictly plant-based
I'm critically important to do
okay Gabrielle or Gabriel
um what what can cause tingling
cessation in a whole food plant-based
diet besides B12 deficiency I presume
you mean tingling sensation kind of uh
fingers and toes that's a sign of a
peripheral typically a sign of
peripheral neuropathy
um why so if let's say you have a
problem with your nerves why would it
show up as tingling in your fingers and
toes well those are the longest nerves
in your body
um so the the the nerve in your toe
actually goes all the way up to your
spinal cord from your toe all the way up
to spinal cord one nerve like one long
skinny teeny little string of spaghetti
but like almost microscopic actually
microscopic all the way up isn't that
amazing one you know you think of cells
as being microscopic this uh this cell
is like you know three feet long
um so you can imagine if there's any
problems with your nerves those are the
nerves that are going to really show it
first right
um these ones are so long and vulnerable
um
and so you get this kind of uh
um that typical thing but it can because
of all sorts of things there's all sorts
of toxins uh medications
um that can do it and so you just really
need to go to a neurologist and they go
through the differential diagnosis all
the various things that can cause it
um there are other nutrition
efficiencies that can do it
um and you just some heavy metal
toxicities can do it
um oh there's autoimmune diseases all
sorts of things so you just got to get
checked out all right what do we got
next
we got
um mechanical
catsy
do I have any short-term effects well do
you have short-term effects with
inspection B12 levels oh
um uh so I presume clinical effects do
you actually feel differently
um in the short term from insufficient
B12 you may not which makes it so
Insidious
um but you can start showing these Club
subclinical
um uh um issues in terms of rising home
assistant or something which you
wouldn't really feel but may have
negative consequences so
um so a regular reliable source of
vitamin B12 is critically important and
uh so for those eating plant-based diets
for example I would recommend either
sufficient vitamin B12 45 Foods or
taking one 2 000 microgram
um uh B12 tablet once a week get all the
B12 you need uh super cheap safe easy
convenient
um and critically important can you
synthesize enough vitamin D during the
warm months to last you throughout
winter okay well yes in terms of enough
vitamin D to live
um I mean that's the whole point is that
during this summer months you know you
got high latitudes you build up enough
and it's stored in your fat and you kind
of live through the winter and then you
get more
um the next year but do you have enough
in your body for Optimal Health
that we don't know the answer
um uh uh and uh and we suspect that it's
probably you probably dip too low and
indeed you see that
um uh of uh you know the that study the
Oxford
um uh City on uh vegans in the UK High
latitude
um vitamin D perfect in the summer dips
um too low during the winter months
um and uh so uh it's probably good when
you're getting into finished sunshine to
supplement your diet with vitamin D and
I would recommend a 2000 international
units of vitamin D3 a day for anyone
getting insufficient Sun doesn't matter
where you live even in the warmer months
if you're inside all day it doesn't
matter how much sun there is outside
you're not going to make enough because
it actually it relies on cutaneous
exposure without sunblock without
clothes what do we have next this is
from Stephanie I don't know if vitamin
D3 is okay for a whole food plant-based
because I've read vitamin d2's vegan
rather than vitamin D3 okay there are
vegan sources of both vitamin D2 which
is Source predominantly from
um fungi from mushrooms
um and vitamin D3 which is Source
predominantly from sheep's wool bud is
also from lichen which is the
kind of been uh algae based
multicellular organism but uh but not an
animal
um uh so uh so yeah you can get vegan
vitamin D3 um
all d2 is vegan but the D3 is probably
preferable just because the studies
showing
um increased increased longevity with
vitamin D supplementation were all done
on vitamin D3
um and so since that's what the studies
were done on we don't know if that
necessarily translates to
um uh D2 so I would just use D3 if you
have a choice if it's important for you
to be vegan you can get a vegan D3 no
problem
[Music]
thank you